Inventory of the Herbert H. Bateman Papers, 1946-1982, 1968-1982
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence, and legal papers concerning statute of limitations on asbestos-related disease, 1980., 11 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
  This includes legal briefs and affidavits sent to Bateman by Robert R. Hatten, of Patten & Wornorn Law Offices, Newport News, Virginia.
  Series 6: Attorney General Opinions
- Correspondence, memoranda, and other documents pertaining to opinions of Virginia Attorney General, 1968-1979., 65 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Mostly opinions rendered at Bateman's request on behalf of constituents on a wide variety of cases.
  Series 7: Auto Clubs
- Five copies of an undated Bateman-sponsored bill authorizing Automobile Clubs to provide certain indemnification services, n.d., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
  Series 8: Auto Inspections
- Correspondence, legislative documents, and background papers regarding bill for annual (instead of semi-annual) automobile safety inspections, 1981-1982., 26 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Includes letters and statistical evidence from opponents of the bill, copies of amendments to and substitute for bill offered by Senator William Fears and minutes of Transportation Safety Board Meeting.
  Also includes letter of 6 January 1982 from Governor John Dalton regarding auto emission inspections.
  Series 9: Banking Legislation
- Report on Legislation Affecting Banking Enacted by the 1980 Session of the Virginia General Assembly, July 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Series 10: Bankruptcy Bill
- Correspondence and other materials relating to [U.S.] Bankruptcy Reform Bill, 1981-1982., 28 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
  Letter of 30 November 1981 from Lawrence Young, of Beneficial Management Corporation, New Jersey, enclosed background information on pending bill and solicited Bateman's assistance in enlisting Virginia Congressmen to co-sponsor bill.
  File includes responses from Congressmen or their offices. Handwritten postscript by Representative G. William Whitehurst applauds Bateman's decision to run for Congress and offers his assistance.
  Series 11: Bingo
- Correspondence and legislative documents regarding state regulation of bingo games, 1979-1980., 54 items. (Box-folder 1:13)
  Includes copies of bills, amendments and conference reports and letters and enclosures from charities sponsoring bingo games, especially concerning House Bill 1219, January-March 1979.
  Series 12: Biomass
- Biomass, 1979-1980. (Box-folder 1:14-17)
  - Correspondence concerning the feasibility of developing regional biomass energy fertilizer plants, 1979-1980., 11 items. (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Correspondence between Bateman and Henry K. Berry, President, and George W. Brooks, Ph.D., of Engineering Incorporated, Hampton, Virginia, regarding feasibility of regional biomass energy/fertilizer plants, 1979-1980., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Includes grant application of Engineering Incorporated and reports and articles on biomass concept.
  - Material related to study of State Senate Biomass Subcommittee on Feasibility of Regional Biomass Energy/Fertilizer Plants, 1979-1980., 16 items. (Box-folder 1:16)
    Includes testimony, correspondence, articles, background papers, and final report (December 1980) of Subcommittee to Virginia Coal and Energy Commission.
  - Materials relating to study of State Senate Biomass Subcommittee, 1979-1980., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Includes committee minutes, testimony, and final report, and articles and memoranda from lumber industry organizations. Duplicates much of the material in Box-folder 1:16.
  Series 13: Budget
- Budget, 1965-1982. (Box-folder 1:18-23)
  - Copy of State Appropriations Act, 1968-1970., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Two drafts of State budget, 1972-1974., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:19)
    Biennium submitted by Governor Linwood Holton.
  - State Appropriations Act and handwritten notes from undated Senate Subcommittee Report on an undated budget, 1972-1974, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Correspondence and legislative papers relating to Bateman's proposed amendments to 1980-1982 Budget Bill, 1980-1982., 13 items. (Box-folder 1:21)
    Includes correspondence with president of Christopher Newport College.
  - Memoranda relating to the State budget, 1980-1982., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:22)
    Includes copy of House amendment and statistical reports of cities and counties on cost to State of salary increases.
  - Correspondence from citizens regarding the 1980-1982 budget, 1981-1982., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:23)
    Most request that the state not reduce funding for specific institutions or programs. Also contains booklet on Virginia's 1982-1984, Effective Budget Highlights.
  Series 14: Busing
- Busing, 1968-1973. (Box-folder 1:24-27)
  - Federal Court Decision, Lee v. Nyquist, on busing case. 1970, 1 item. Photocopy. (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Correspondence between Bateman and members of Congress regarding court-ordered busing, 1971, 1973, 63 items. (Box-folder 1:25)
    Bateman wrote each members of Congress in August 1971 expressing his opposition to busing, and received replies (with enclosed news releases, Congressional Record, excerpts, and copies of resolutions) from many of them.
  - Correspondence from Bateman's constituents regarding the issue of court-ordered busing, 1968-1976., 28 items. (Box-folder 1:26)
    Letters from individuals and organizations urging Bateman to oppose busing and carbon copies of Bateman's replies.
  - Various materials relating to court-ordered busing., 26 items. (Box-folder 1:27)
    Correspondence, news releases, and newspaper clippings expressing Bateman's refutation of a charge by political opponent that he supported busing; correspondence with and newsletters of an organization, "Save Our Neighborhood Schools" (S.O.N.S.) with whom Bateman cooperated; copy of undated Joint resolution which Bateman sponsored calling for amendment to U.S. Constitution forbidding assignment to schools on the basis of race, religion, or national origins.
  Series 15: Capital Punishment
- Copy of article on capital punishment and the Eighth Amendment from Ohio State Law Journal, 1978., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:28)
  Series 16: Christopher Newport College
- Letter from Jane and George Webb, professors in the Department of Physics, thanking Bateman for his support of Christopher Newport College, 9 November 1981., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:29)
  Series 17: Child Auto Safety
- Letter to Bateman from Joseph Zanga, Medical College of Virginia, inviting Bateman to Child Restraint seminars, 10 September 1981., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:30)
  See also Seat Belt Laws, series 172; and Transportation, series 199-202.
  Series 18: Claims Subcommittee, 1982
- Material relating to work of State Senate Claims Subcommittee, 1982., 41 items. (Box-folder 1:31)
  See also Courts of Justice, series 31 (Box 3), for more on the Norfolk Savings and Loan Corporation.
  Bills for relief of individuals and for relief of Norfolk Savings and Loan Corporation, including file of exhibits pertaining to latter case.
  Series 19: Coal Tax
- Material relating to proposed coal severance tax, 1975-1976, 1982., 22 items. (Box-folder 1:32)
  Includes copies of bills, photocopies of newspaper articles, surveys, reports, and testimony.
  Series 20: Coal and Energy Commission, 1979-1982
- Coal and Energy Commission, 1979-1982. (Box 1-2)
  Seeb also uranium mining, series 208.
  - Coal and Engergy Commission, 1979. (Box-folder 1:33-37)
    - Memoranda, reports and other materials related to Bateman's service on Virginia Coal and Energy Commission, 1979., 10 items. (Box-folder 1:33)
      File includes notice of Bateman's appointment to Committee (3 May 1979), and memoranda concerning alternative energy sources during gas shortage of 1979.
    - U.S. Department of Energy report, Environmental Analysis of Synthetic Liquid Fuels, 12 July 1979, 2 items. Photocopy. (Box-folder 1:34)
    - American Electrical Power Service Corporation Report and executive summary of report, A Comparison of the impacts of Providing Residential Service from Coal Based Electric and SNG Gas Systems, September 1979., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:35)
    - Reports, memoranda and articles regarding research on coal based and other synthetic fuel production in Virginia, 1979., 13 items. (Box-folder 1:36)
    - Articles and reports on alternative energy sources and Directory of Energy Expertise for 1980-1981, 1979-1981., 4 items. (Box-folder 1:37)
  - Coal and Engergy Commission, 1980. (Box 1-2)
    - Assorted materials relating to Bateman's work on Virginia Coal and Energy Commission, 1980., 11 items. (Box-folder 1:38)
      File includes list of Commission members (1980), House bill on Solar Energy Programs, list of publications from Division of Mineral Resources, and information on Virginia topographical maps.
    - Report of Coal and Energy Commission to the Governor and General Assembly, 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:39)
    - U.S. Department of Energy reports and proposals regarding alternative fuels production, March-May 1980., 14 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Including lists and addresses of conference participants and text of questions and answers.
    - Material pertaining to work of Coal Subcommittee of Coal and Energy Commission, 1980., 4 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Including December 1980 Subcommittee report and reviews on coal situation from Chase Manhattan Bank and Bethlehem Steel.
    - Materials pertaining to work of Energy Preparedness Subcommittee of Coal and Energy Commission, 1980., 5 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Including report on energy study exchange between Virginia and Brazil, report on van pooling, and subcommittee's 1980 report.
    - Reports and memoranda pertaining to work of Geothermal Subcommittee of Coal and Energy Commission, 1980., 10 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
      File includes several reports on aspects of geothermal policies prepared by National Conference of State Legislatures and 1980 report of subcommittee.
    - Reports of the Electric Power Subcommittee and Hydroelectric Power Subcommittee of Coal and Energy Commission, 1980., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
    - 1980 report of Oil and Gas Subcommittee of Coal and Energy Commission and report on oil and gas development in Virginia by state oil and gas inspector, 1980., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Oil and gas statutes of Arkansas, Louisiana, and Mississippi used as background material by Oil and Gas Subcommittee of Coal and Energy Commission, 1980., 5 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Material related to work of Oil and Gas Subcommittee of Coal and Energy Commission, 1980., 28 items. (Box-folder 2:8)
      Including photocopies of oil and gas statutes of Oklahoma and West Virginia, and drafts of bills and amendments regarding oil and gas conservation in Virginia.
    - Materials relating to work of Oil and Gas Subcommittee of Coal and Energy Commission, 1980., 18 items. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Including multiple copies of statements by industry, corporations and consultants and report of subcommittee (8 December 1980).
  - Coal and Engergy Commission, 1981. (Box-folder 2:10-15)
    - Membership list of Coal and Energy Commission, 1981., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Commission and subcommittee materials, 1981., 6 items. (Box-folder 2:11)
      Items include minutes of a meeting of the Coal and Energy Commission, 16 October 1981, testimony of Dr. Peter Montague before commission, 28 April 1981, and minutes of Renewable Resources Subcommittee, 17 September 1981.
    - Documents relating to Ground Storage Export Facility: testimony of John P. Fishwick, Chairman and Chief Executive Officer of Norfolk and Western Railway, and letter from Chairman of VCEC Coal Subcommittee, 1981, 3 items. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Materials relating to small-scale hydroelectric development, 1980-1981., 4 items. (Box-folder 2:13)
      Letters, memoranda and handbook from William R. Ferguson of the National Conference of State Legislatures, as background for 9 September 1981 meeting of VCEC Renewable Resources Subcommittee.
    - Documents relating to utilization of recycled motor oil, August 1981., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:14)
      Testimony of James W. Heizer, Executive Director of the Virginia Gasoline Retailers Association, and copy of relevant Tennessee statute.
    - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports concerning U.S. Strategic Petroleum Reserve (SPR), 1981., 42 items. (Box-folder 2:15)
      Includes two copies of 17 July 1981 memo to VCEC members from state attorney, information file on SPR from Norfolk and Western Railway, Department of Energy's 1981 Annual Report on SPR program, and unidentified file of documents and clippings, mostly pertaining to prospect of SPR storage facility at the Worthy Mine, Smythe County, Virginia, probably furnished by the Texas-based Saltville Underground Storage Company.
  - Coal and Engergy Commission, 1982. (Box-folder 2:16-20)
    - Minutes of meetings of Coal and Energy Commission, 1982, with membership lists of its subcommittees, and copies of assembly bills and resolutions requesting specific investigations by VCEC, 1982., 11 items. (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Documents relating to the work of the Virginia Coal and Energy Commission, 1982., 32 items. (Box-folder 2:17)
      January 1982 report of the commission, bills and resolutions providing for uranium mining, mineral exploration on state lands, and inspection of utilities for conservation efficiency, and background memoranda (1980-1981) on exploration on state lands.
    - Report on small-scale hydroelectric policy, April 1982, sent to members of Renewable Energy Subcommittee of VCEC by William Ferguson of the National Conference of State Legislatures, 1982., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:18)
    - Memoranda and minutes relating to meeting of Oil and Gas Subcommittee, 6 July 1982., 6 items. (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Copy of proposed Regulations for Conservation of Oil and Gas Resources and Well Spacing, October 1982, and announcement of public hearing on proposed regulations. 1982., 4 items. (Box-folder 2:20)
  Series 21: Coastal Zone Land Management Act
- Coastal Zone Land Management Act (CZLM Act) (Box 2-3)
  - Background material relating to Virginia Coastal Zone Land Management Program, 1975-1977., 29 items. (Box-folder 2:21)
    Including working papers and minutes of meetings of Virginia Coastal Study Commission (on which Bateman served), old Assembly bills, and position papers from individuals, business groups and public agencies.
    See also Wetlands, series 230.
  - Materials relating to Virginia's Coastal Zone Land Program, January-Spring 1978., 20 items. (Box-folder 2:22)
    Including copies of bills, handwritten notes of Virginia Coastal Study Commission, memoranda, proposals from individuals and county/city officials in Virginia, and report by law student at Marshall-Wythe School of Law.
  - Materials on Virginia's coastal land management policy, August-December 1978., 28 items. (Box-folder 2:23)
    Mostly statements and commentaries by individuals and, especially, county and city governments on this policy.
  - Materials relating to General Assembly consideration of CZLM bill, especially H.R. 403, January 1979, including multiple copies of bills, resolutions and amendments and position papers by individuals and organizations., 44 items. (Box-folder 2:24)
    Also includes Bateman's alternative bill (S. 741) introduced 15 January 1979, and letter of 16 January 1979 explaining his reasons for sponsoring this bill.
  - Materials relating to coastal zone land management and H.R. 403, January-March 1979., 47 items. (Box-folder 2:25)
    Including multiple copies of bills, roll call vote tallies, reports and memoranda, position papers from business organizations, Bateman's letter to editor of Daily Press on H.R. 403 (29 January 1979), and file of newspaper clippings on H.R. 403 in Virginia Assembly.
  - Materials relating to Virginia zone land management policy, May-October 1979., 13 items. (Box-folder 2:26)
    Including drafts of bills and proposed bills and reports, and minutes and reports of Virginia State Chamber of Commerce.
  - Materials relating to General Assembly's consideration of H.R. 403 and alternative bills, including multiple copies of bills and substitutes, memoranda and commentaries on bill by business organizations, n.d., [1978-1979]., 38 items. (Box-folder 2:27)
    Also includes Bateman's personnel position papers, handwritten list of "opponnents" of bill and legislative history ("track record") of bill.
  - Undated background materials relating to coastal zone land management policies, especially reports and bibliographies on land management, n.d., 9 items. (Box-folder 2:28)
    Includes publication, An Analysis: Virginia Beach as a Resort Community.
  - Legal Authorities Report, prepared by Office of Attorney General for Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Resources, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and notes relating to Virginia Coastal Zone Management Program, December 1979-1980., 14 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
  Series 22: Coastal Zone Land Management Bill
- Coastal Zone Land Management Bill (Box-folder 3:3-6)
  - Documents relating to 1980 Bill to amend 1972 Virginia Wetlands Act: memos and acts regarding federal coastal programs, multiple copies of working drafts of bill which Bateman later sponsored, 1972-1980., 17 items. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Documents (through 30 January 1980) regarding bill(s) to amend Virginia Wetlands Act of 1972, 1972-1980., 28 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Includes 1978 report of the Secretary of Commerce and Resources, letter and enclosures from Governor John Dalton, copies of bills which Bateman sponsored, letters and suggestions from lobbying groups, and extracts from testimony.
  - Legislative papers and correspondence (February 1980) regarding General Assembly consideration of several bills (including one which Bateman sponsored) to amend Virginia Wetlands Act of 1972, 1972-1980., 35 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
    Includes copies of bills, amendments, roll call, vote tabulations, planning and budget impact statements, and letters from constituents.
  - Documents relating to House Bill No. 206, to amend Virginia Wetlands Act, 1972., 46 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
    This file features items relating to legislative battle over opposing version of bill between Bateman and delegate George Grayson, of Williamsburg. It includes letters from Grayson to other Virginia Senators to solicit support of his version, letters to and from Governor John Dalton, arranging his veto of bill once Bateman's amendments failed, editorial commentary on history of bill, undated amendments and correspondence, roll call vote tabulations and summary of Assembly action on Senate and House bills.
  Series 23: Commendations
- Letters of thanks and commendation to Bateman for his legislative work from such bodies as the City of Newport News, the Office of Governor Mills Godwin, Old Dominion University, University of Virginia Student Council President Larry Sabato, the Virginia Seafood Council, the United Mineworkers, and many others, 1965-1975., 36 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
  Series 24: Conflict of Interest
- Conflict of Interest, 1970-1981. (Box-folder 3:8-9)
  - Documents and correspondence relating to Virginia's Conflict of Interest Law and Bateman's adherence to it, 1970-1975., 62 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
    Includes Bateman's annual disclosure forms correspondence relating to possible conflicts of interest, and some material relating to amending of act.
  - Bateman's disclosure forms and correspondence relating to compliance with Conflict of Interest Laws, 1976-1981., 32 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
  Series 25: Consolidation
- Report and correspondence regarding possible consolidation of Hampton and Newport News, 1978-1979., 5 items. (Box-folder 3:10)
  Copy of confidential 1978 preliminary report forwarded to Bateman by Thomas P. Chisman, Chairman of study committee.
  Series 26: Constitutional Offices
- Letter with accompanying charts from J. T. Shropshire, Chairman of Virginia Compensation Board, regarding formula for funding constitutional officers in Virginia, 28 May 1982., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:11)
  Series 27: Consumer Credit
- Consumer Credit, 1969-1975. (Box-folder 3:12-15)
  - Reports on consumer credit laws in Arkansas (1969) and Washington State (1971), 1969-1971., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Background papers relating to work of Consumer Credit Study Commission (of which Bateman was a member), 1972-1973, including reports on Wisconsin Consumer Act, photocopy of article in the University of Richmond Law Review and a draft of a proposed consumer credit enforcement code, 1972-1973., 9 items. (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Materials relating to work of Consumer Credit Study Commission, 1973., 8 items. (Box-folder 3:14)
    Including handwritten notes and minutes of 15 May 1973 meeting, summary of state credit laws, and proposed changes in Virginia laws.
  - Bills and acts approved affecting consumer credit, 1973-1975., 14 items. Copy. (Box-folder 3:15)
  Series 28: Consumer Protection
- Consumer Protection, 1966-1986, n.d. (Box-folder 3:16-21)
  - Assorted material on consumer protection laws in Virginia including January 1975 memorandum by Attorney General Andrew Miller on Virginia's Fair Trade Act, undated report on "Drug Bioequivalence," and undated compilation of Virginia consumer laws, 1970-1976, n.d., 14 items. (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Reports and memoranda from the Council of State Governments Southern Conference, 1972, on consumer issues, including list of state consumer office and summary of June 1972 meeting, 1972., 7 items. (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Materials pertaining to activities of Consumer Protection Committee of the Southern Legislative Conference of the Council of State Governments, 1972-1974., 25 items. (Box-folder 3:18)
    Including agendas for and summaries of November 1972 and January 1973 meetings, summary of suggested state legislation for 1973, and council booklet on modernizing state constitutions, 1966-1972.
  - Materials relating to work of Consumer Protection Committee of the Council of State Legislatures, 1975-1976., 14 items. (Box-folder 3:19)
    Including reports on consumer complaints in the south, public service commissions in the south, Council's suggested state legislation for 1975, and materials relating to Council's 1975 meeting in Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Materials relating to November 1975 meeting of Consumer Protection Committee of the Council of State Governments Southern Conference, 1974-1975., 5 items. (Box-folder 3:20)
    Including index of Federal Publications on consumer issues, 15 August 1975 issue of Consumer News, and copy of federal government publication, State Consumer Action: Summary '74.
  - Correspondence and other materials relating to activities of Southern Legislative Conference Consumer Protection Committee (SLCCPC), 1980-1982., 16 items. (Box-folder 3:21)
    Includes announcements and reservation forms for SLC CPC meetings and material sent to Bateman by officials of Kroger Food Stores.
  Series 29: Corrections
- Corrections, 1971-1981. (Box-folder 3:22-24)
  - Correspondence and reports on Virginia's correctional system, 1971-1974., 18 items. (Box-folder 3:22)
    Includes articles, suggested legislation, and letters from constituents, lobbyists, and state officials on prison reform, and 220 page, 1974 report on Bland Correctional Farm and 13 Field Units in Virginia.
  - Correspondence, newsletters and reports regarding Virginia's correctional system, 1974-1981., 25 items. (Box-folder 3:23)
    including letters relating to individual prisoners, and newsletters and fact sheets from Director of Department of Correction.